Finding Aid for the J. León Helguera Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
J. León Helguera Papers
2016
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0566
1.25 Linear Feet
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains primary sources related to the training program for the United States Peace Corps-Columbia project. This seven-week training program in the summer of 1961 for the first group of Peace Corps volunteers to be sent to Colombia took place at Rutgers University in Brunswick, New Jersey. The materials include lecture notes, examinations, schedules, and lists of volunteers. In the correspondence files are many letters to Professor Helguera from the Peace Corps volunteers, including those who were selected for service in Columbia and those who were not, and his replies. Also part of this collection are materials relating to the United States Army’s Caribbean school at Fort Gulick in what was then the Canal Zone in Panama. This school’s purpose was to conduct military courses for Latin American students. Dr. Helguera visited there, courtesy of staff member Major Russell Rumsey in 1962.
The materials in this collection will be of special interest to those working in topics relating to the first Peace Corps volunteers sent to Columbia.
Biographical Sketch
J. León Helguera was born in the Greenwich Village of New York City and spent part of his childhood in Mexico City. After graduating from high school and serving in the United States Army, he returned to Mexico City, earning a B.A. from Mexico City College. Returning to the United States, Helguera was briefly engaged in antiquarian book selling, and then entered the graduate history program at the University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill. After earning his M.A., he moved with his wife and children to Colombia for a year of research for his dissertation on the Colombian military figure General T.C. de Mosquera. He obtained his Ph.D from the University of North Carolina, and then taught at North Carolina State University until 1962 when he joined the faculty at Vanderbilt University. He is now Emeritus Professor of History, Vanderbilt University.
Dr. Helguera has published extensively on Latin American topics and received many academic honors. In his retirement he has continued to be active in speaking and writing on Colombia and other Latin American topics. Because of his knowledge of Colombia, he was instrumental in the preparation of the first group of Peace Corps volunteers to be sent to that country. He taught and mentored these young men in their training conducted at Rutgers University, Brunswick, New Jersey during the summer of 1961.
- Box Listing
  - Correspondence---Incoming---Beyer-Downing (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence---Incoming---Greenlaw-Grubb (Folder 2)
  - Correspondence---Incoming---Haselby-Helguera, G. (Folder 3)
  - Correspondence---Incoming---Helguera, L.-Limantour (Folder 4)
  - Correspondence---Incoming---McMahon-Quintana (Folder 5)
  - Correspondence---Incoming---Radley-Torres (Folder 6)
  - Correspondence---Incoming---Whalen-Zwerling (Folder 7)
  - Correspondence---Outgoing, August 24, 1948-January 14, 1950 (Folder 8)
  - Correspondence---Outgoing, May 8, 1950-December 2, 1950 (Folder 9)
  - Correspondence---Outgoing, January 27, 1951-June 11, 1961 (Folder 10)
  - Correspondence---Outgoing, June 13, 1961-December 17, 1961 (Folder 11)
  - Peace Corps---Training Program-Colombia Project---Training materials (Including Lectures, Examinations, Schedules) (Folder 12)
  - Peace Corps---Training Program-Colombia Project---Expense Accounts (Folder 13)
  - Peace Corps---Training Program-Colombia Project---Evaluation of Program by Volunteer Bruce Lane (Folder 14)
  - Peace Corps---Training Program-Colombia Project---Lists of Volunteers (Folder 15)
  - Peace Crops---Training Program-Colombia Project---Follow-up Report after One Month (Folder 16)
  - Peace Crops---Training Program-Colombia Project---Follow-up Report after Four Months (Folder 17)
  - Peace Corps---Research Materials---Third Annual Report, 1961-Centro de Estudios sobre Desarrollo Economico (Folder 18)
  - United States Army Caribbean School---Escuela USARCARIB---Propecto Ilustrado (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - United States Army Caribbean School---USARCARIB School---Staff and Faculty Guide (Folder 2)
  - United States Army Caribbean School---Escuela USARCARIB---Guia para Estudiantes (Folder 3)
  - United States Army Caribbean School---Escuela USARCARIB---Recuerdo de su Visita (Folder 4)
  - Pamphlets---Colombia, Denmark (Folder 5)
  - Pamphlets---Guia del Archivo Nacional de Historia del Ecuador-Epoca Colonial by Juan R. FreileGranizo (Folder 6)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1950-1961 (Folder 7)
  - Photographs---Peace Corps-Colombia Project and Unidentified (Folder 8)
  - Academic Career---Vanderbilt University (Folder 9)